<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Advice, sent in a letter from an elder brother, to a younger. Which he missed of by being abscent, since occasionally printed, it relating to remedying and reforming severall abuses in the Common Wealth, by severall practisers pretending equitie and conscience in the High Court of Chancery, and that unsetled, irregular unlimmited Court of Probates, who also act against the law of God, and the law of England, as in the reading thereof may be observed and bewayled, and it is hoped, may be of publick concernment, and profit; wherefore the author hath been at this charge of printing it.</title>
            <author>Burt, Nathaniel, fl. 1644-1655.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 102 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78010</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B6140</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E838_8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207429</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866479</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866479</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118754</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78010)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118754)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 127:E838[8])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Advice, sent in a letter from an elder brother, to a younger. Which he missed of by being abscent, since occasionally printed, it relating to remedying and reforming severall abuses in the Common Wealth, by severall practisers pretending equitie and conscience in the High Court of Chancery, and that unsetled, irregular unlimmited Court of Probates, who also act against the law of God, and the law of England, as in the reading thereof may be observed and bewayled, and it is hoped, may be of publick concernment, and profit; wherefore the author hath been at this charge of printing it.</title>
                  <author>Burt, Nathaniel, fl. 1644-1655.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication to Cromwell signed: Cap. Nathanael Burt.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May. 12".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Court of Chancery --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118754:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ADVICE, Sent in a LETTER <hi>From an</hi> Elder <hi>Brother,</hi> to a Younger.</p>
            <p>Which he miſſed of by being abſcent, ſince occaſionally Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, it relating to remedying and reforming ſeverall Abuſes in the <hi>COMMON WEALTH,</hi> by ſeverall Practiſers pretending <hi>Equitie</hi> and <hi>Conſcience</hi> in the High Court of <hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery,</hi> and that unſetled, irregular unlimmited Court of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates,</hi> who alſo Act againſt the Law of God, and the Law of <hi>England,</hi> as in the reading thereof may be obſerved and bewayled, and it is hoped, may be of Publick Concernmen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and Profit; wherefore the Author hath been at this charge of Printing it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Who riſeth up with me againſt the wicked? Who taketh my part a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the evill doers? If the Lord had not helped me, my ſoul had been put to ſilence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wilt thou have any thing to do with the stool of wickedneſs which ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gineth miſchief in the Law?</hi> Mr. Tindalls tranſlation, Pſal. 94. <hi>If a Ruler hearken to Lies, all his ſervants are wicked.</hi> Prov. 29.12.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>None calleth for Juſtice, nor any pleadeth for truth, they truſt in vanity, and ſpeak lies, they conceive miſchief, and bring forth iniquitie.</hi> Eſay 59.4.</p>
            <p>Of falſe Judges aſſigned, King <hi>Alfred</hi> ordained ſuch Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that the wrong they do to God, whoſe Vicege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents they are, and have conuſance to judge Offenders, that firſt they be judged to make ſatisfaction to thoſe they have hurt, that are parties Plaintiffs. <hi>The Book called,</hi> The <hi>Mirrour</hi> of <hi>Juſtices.</hi> pag. 207.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Author 1655.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:118754:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118754:2"/>
            <head>TO HIS HIGHNESSE, <hi>O. CROMWELL,</hi> Lord Protector of the Common Wealth of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> And to His Honorable Councellors and Aſſiſtants.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>O. CROMWELL,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Am moved by Gods Spirit this preſent 24. of <hi>May,</hi> 1655 to write this to You, and thoſe that aſſiſt You in Council, for your leiſurely peruſal, with the other lines that belong there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, and alſo to preſent them, by the ſpirit of God, who is the King of all the Earth, and reigneth <hi>over the Heathen,</hi> and of a truth will be found no reſpector of Perſons, though many that are in places to Judge the <hi>People,</hi> give falſe Judgement, and <hi>reſpect Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> both in the <hi>High Court</hi> of <hi>Chancery,</hi> And that Illegall, Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, Irregular, Unlimmited <hi>Court,</hi> now called a Court of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates,</hi> &amp;c. in which is executed more <hi>the will of man</hi> then the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lord, they reſpecting the Perſons, and Profitts one of another, as they do yet in <hi>Chancery,</hi> although in the Ordinance for <hi>Regulating</hi> and limmitting the <hi>High Court</hi> of <hi>Chancery,</hi> it is Ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, <hi>fol.</hi> 523. That for the future there be no more cauſe of juſt Complaints from the People.</p>
            <p>SIR, it is hoped good things will be found in You; <hi>Jehu</hi> told <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> 2 <hi>Chro,</hi> 19.2, 3 <hi>For ſuch a thing he had provoked the Lord to be wrath with him; Nevertheleſſe good things are found in thee,</hi> and that You will ſet Judges over the People of the <hi>Common-Wealth</hi> of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> You having accepted the Stile of Lord Protector thereof, and ſworn to Govern theſe Nations accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the <hi>Lawes, Statutes</hi> and <hi>Cuſtomes,</hi> ſeeking their Peace, and cauſing <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Law</hi> to be equall Adminiſtred; The Lord God of our Fathers enable Your <hi>Highneſs</hi> to put in ſuch men to Judge between the People, that may be men of Truth, fearing God, and hating Covetouſneſs, as <hi>Jethro</hi> adviſed <hi>Moſes, Exod.</hi> 18.21. the <hi>People</hi> have been long abuſed and oppreſſed by lying unſatiable extorting, unfaithfull, unconſcionable Lawyers, and men in pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Judicature, to the diſhonor of God, and the deſtruction of
<pb facs="tcp:118754:3"/> the <hi>Nations,</hi> and their great reproach, for ſin is a reproach to a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple or Nation But Juſtice or Righteouſneſs exalteth a Nation. <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.34. <hi>and lying lipps are an abomination to the Lord,</hi> but they that deal truly are his delight. <hi>Prov.</hi> 2.22. then all lying men in place of Judicature, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ying Lawyers that deal not truly, <hi>are an Abomination to the Lord;</hi> The Apoſtle, who knew all Gods Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.27. For he muſt firſt know it before he could declare it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, ſaith, <hi>God ordaines Powers, for the Peoples Weale, or good, and ſuch are called Gods Miniſters, and are to attend continually for that very end, or thing, for the Peoples good, and well-being, if the People do well; but they are to take Vengeance, if the People do evil, and to ſuch ministring Perſons ought People to be obedient, or ſubject un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, not becauſe of their wrath, but for Conſcience ſake,</hi> Your Highneſs, aſſiſted with your Council, hath begun to limit and regulate that unconſcionable Court of <hi>Chancery,</hi> and lying delaying <hi>Practiſers,</hi> and to pull down their extortions by your <hi>Ordinance,</hi> made <hi>August</hi> 22. 1654, though they are loath to obey it; Oh judge for the Lord, and limmit and regulate that <hi>unchriſtian corrupt Court,</hi> ſtiled a <hi>Court of Probates,</hi> &amp;c, for the <hi>Civillians</hi> muſt confeſſe, their Law is a Sea full of <hi>Waves,</hi> and as uncertain as the preſent Judges mindes thereof, but the grounds of our <hi>Common Law</hi> have from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning been lay'd with ſuch deep <hi>Wiſdom, Policy and Providence,</hi> as they do provide for and meet with almoſt all <hi>Caſes</hi> that can fall out in our <hi>Common Wealth;</hi> Th'Imperiall Power, th'immeiate Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer under God and Chriſt, is ſetled in Your <hi>Perſon,</hi> with Your Council, and all <hi>Writts, Proceſſes, Commiſſions, Patents, Grants</hi> and other things in Your <hi>Name,</hi> they are to run as the 2 &amp; 3, &amp; 33 <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles</hi> of <hi>Government,</hi> declared <hi>Decem</hi> 16. 1653. and from You to be diſtributed in all Courts, they acting and doing in the <hi>Name</hi> of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver</hi> Lord <hi>Protector,</hi> ſhould act juſtly and truely; and the <hi>Pen-man</hi> hereof ſhall exhort all People with the words of <hi>Paul.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.1, 2. <hi>to make ſupplycations</hi> for Your <hi>Highneſs,</hi> &amp;c. and all you ſhall preferr to Judge between the People, and deal truly therein, that ſo we may lead quiet <hi>and peaceable lives in all godlineſs</hi> &amp; <hi>honesty;</hi> for falſe Judges, and falſe &amp; lying <hi>Practiſers</hi> about the <hi>Law, under them, muſt be a more intollerable and ahhominable thing then Warr; beleeves Yours, while GOD is with you, and you with him.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> Nathanael Burt.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:118754:3"/>
            <head>AN EPISTLE DEDICATORY, TO M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. WILLIAM WHETSTONE, His hoped for Freind in the Truth.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat a man ſhould Dedicate his caſe to one he is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to ſue in the Law, one would think ſhould ſeem a Juggle, or a Paradox; but it will not be ſo found in this, and I ſhall cleer it to you, or any elſe; for in the <hi>Mirrour</hi> of <hi>Juſtices, pages. 156, 157, 158.</hi> Our Ancestors, if the partie would not confeſſe that had done any falſitie to a man in deed or word, where there was no wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to teſtifie the truth, they were ſuffered to enter Battell, if E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualls, for Declaration thereof, or proof thereof, and ſometimes they proved by Witneſſes, <hi>ſaith the Author;</hi> for if a man hath done any falſity to me in deed or in word, whereof he is appealed or impeached in Judgement, if he deny it, it is lawfull for me to prove the Action, either by <hi>Jury,</hi> or by my Body, or by the body of one Witneſs: Now that Battell is laid aſide, yet by Jury and Witneſs a man may prove his Action, or Appeale; and I having ſpoken to you, and finding you ſo reall and juſt, and honeſt, in your Diſcovery of the matter related in theſe following lines, and confeſſion thereunto, and ſince this our Appeal to Equity and Law is a Combating, and that the Victory is holden for
<pb facs="tcp:118754:4"/> 
               <hi>truth,</hi> and you a Witneſs therein, I have placed you upon the front of the Battell, and have dedicated it to you, that in this fraudulent mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, whereof doubtleſs you have been ignorant, as a faithfull and Coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Champion or Combitant, you may maintain the truth hereof to this evill lying World, and in your anſwer in <hi>Chancery,</hi> quit your ſelf like a Chriſtian man, and thereby keep a good Conſcience, void of Offence. <hi>Thomas Walton</hi> hath confeſſed the cancelling of the old Writings to our Father in his Houſe, though not by his own hand, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prill</hi> the Eleventh, <hi>1655.</hi> But would not confeſſe <hi>Francis Riche<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Habitation. Sir, on Saturday, <hi>Aprill</hi> the Seventh, toward Evening, I was with Mr. <hi>Thomas Ellis,</hi> to have delivered this Letter to my Brother <hi>John Burt,</hi> where he lodgeth in <hi>More-fields,</hi> and his Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lord told me and Mr. <hi>Ellis,</hi> that he and his Wife and Children were gone out of Towne, and that he had no ſervant left there in being to anſwer for them, or belonging to them, ſo that not knowing when he may return, I having been at the paines of penning of it, and added ſince ſomething of Court Abuſes, and wiſhing his repentance, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendmennt, and theirs alſo, that this iniquity be not his perpetuall loſs and undoing, but that he may be ſaved in the day of Chriſts appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; though thereby he hath ſought my temporall ruine, and I not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing certaine of his return, that I might have ſeen how he would have received my Councell, or rebuke herein, and anſwered there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto next unto Gods glory, and <hi>Englands</hi> Laws, I claime ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to, and any Dammages or loſſes I have received by him and his Complices therein beſide my trouble and grief thereby (and the expences and loſſe which you have already ſeen and felt by him, and through him and his procurement) who as it is beleeved, never deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved or ought to have had any ſuch uſage from him; or any of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices, abbetors or Confederates, and that now it is diſcovered, and come to my knowledge, ſo much as concerneth you, you are by Law an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to me; who am the Eldeſt ſon of my Father, and ſole Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrator by Law of my Fathers Eſtate, and by the Seal of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative Court, unto whom <hi>John Burt</hi> became bound in a bond of <hi>500. l.</hi> to fulfill certain Articles which were ſealed between us twelve dayes after our Fathers Funerall, and Sixteen dayes after his diſceaſe
<pb facs="tcp:118754:4"/> wherein he tyes or bindes me the eldeſt Son to ſue Letters of Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration out of the Prerogative Court in <hi>500. l.</hi> alſo, and himſelf with me to Diſcover to the utmoſt of our knowledge the ſaid Eſtate, <hi>viz.</hi> All and ſingular the Goods, Chattells, Plate, ready Money, Leaſes, and all other things whatſoever, which any way did, or doth concern the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of the ſaid diſceaſed, which B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd, Witneſſes, and adminiſtration I have ſhewed you, and he having had in his hand and Poſseſſion ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Writings and Leaſes of your Fathers, which have continued with our Father ever ſince <hi>Anno 1639.</hi> and the uſe made by our Father, Recited in his Book of Accounts written with his own hand, untill the Chriſtmas before he dyed, which reſts with me, and he dyed <hi>June</hi> the <hi>12th, 1654.</hi> Now you being the Principall Witneſſe herein, and next unto my ſelf, the neereſt concerned both in the abuſe, Charge and loſs paſt, and of ſuffering for future. I having uſed your Name in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating the matter of mine and your abuſe, and ſince he is abſcent, that I cannot have his preſent Anſwer. I am conſtrained to publiſh it in Print, that my wrongs, loſſes and falſe judgement given againſt me, may appear to you, and through you to the World, you being the grand Witneſs, and others alſo, and that can here diſcover concerning the fraude and Concealement of the ſaid Writings belonging to you and your Father diſceaſed; and I hope by this to finde much more of my Fathers concealed Eſtate. And it being commanded, <hi>That the hand of the Witneſſe be firſt upon him that is to ſuffer.</hi> Deut. <hi>17.7. And that the Father and Mother of the Rebellious or ſtubborn Son, which would not heare the voice of his Father or Mother, ſhould lay hands on him, and bring him before the Elders of the City, That he might ſuffer for that he would not hear and obey them,</hi> it being an evill Example in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and not to be ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; This Premiſed to you, with my Love and Well-wiſhings to you.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Aprill the 18. 1655.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>I reſt yours for the truehs ſake,</hi> NATHANAEL B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RT.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:118754:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118754:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>ADVICE, Sent in a LETTER</hi> From an <hi>Elder</hi> Brother, <hi>to a Younger.</hi> And <hi>Iſaac</hi> trembled very exceedingly, and ſaid, thy Brother came with ſubtilty, and hath taken away thy bleſſing, And <hi>Eſau</hi> ſaid, Is he not rightly named <hi>Jaacob,</hi> for he hath ſupplanted me theſe two times, he took away my birth-right, Behold, now he hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away my bleſſing.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>JOHN BURT,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am not ignorant, that <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel</hi> were na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall Brethren, and that <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Iſmael</hi> were naturall brethren, or taken by <hi>Abraham</hi> ſo to be, who was their naturall Father, as well as by others, though they were by two ſeverall Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and <hi>Eſau</hi> and <hi>Jaacob</hi> were ſo both by one Father and Mother, as <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel</hi> were by one man, and one Woman, which Scripture ſetteth forth; and though <hi>Cain</hi> the elder Brother, ſlew <hi>Abell</hi> the younger Brother, in thoſe dayes, as Mr. <hi>Sparkes</hi> his younger ſon, in your memory, ſlew his Elder Brother, and ſuffered the Law for it; ſo you ungrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly and unnaturally left word at my Houſe, <hi>September</hi> 8. 1654. with two ſeverall Perſons in my abſcence, That my laſt glaſſe was run, and bid them to tell me ſo from you. And
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118754:6"/> when you had buried me alive, <hi>December,</hi> 1654. in <hi>Luds-gate,</hi> in your rage and Malice, to bring about your conſpired ends, you having no juſt cauſe againſt me in Law to ground an acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon, or to file a Declaration againſt me, Wherefore you were fain the 2 Court Day after to withdraw your own Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of 500. l. though your Attorney <hi>Baines,</hi> againſt his Oath, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litiouſly moved the Court againſt a Non-ſuit therein, ſaying, he could not find the Bond, and he knew he had declared there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper Bench,</hi> the <hi>Michaelmas</hi> Terme was 12 Moneths before, yet in the mean time, with my ungracious Son in law <hi>Peter Tompſon,</hi> you both of you offered to ſweare then in the Court of <hi>Probates,</hi> you had no Action then upon me, which was a Lie, as two witneſſes can yet teſtifie, viz. <hi>Thomas Ellis</hi> and <hi>John Brooke.</hi> And though you are my half Brother, and had buryed me there alive, to bring about your malitious fraudu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ends, and thereby to procure to your ſelf of thoſe unjuſt and unrighteous Judges, letters of Adminiſtration, againſt the Law of God, and of <hi>England,</hi> as though my glaſſe of Life had been run indeed, and I departed, out of this life (for Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, let it be well obſerved) is but a Civill Death, the Law maketh it ſo. And ſure you and your Complices looked on me ſo to be indeed, when illegally, unrighteouſly, and irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, they granted Letters of Adminiſtration to you, a ſecond ſonne, by a ſecond ventor, which by Law is unanſwerable, Thus hath your dealings been like a treacherous, falſe, deceitfull, unfaithfull, unchriſtian, unholy, unnaturall Brother, in which our Fathers Name cannot but be diſhonoured: I have read in Scripture alſo, That <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Lot,</hi> though their Heards<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſtrove together, yet <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaid to <hi>Lot; Let there be no ſtrife, I pray thee between me and thee; and between my Heards-men and thy Heards-men, for we are Brethren:</hi> Yet it is written, <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> and <hi>Lot</hi> had two ſeverall men to be their naturall Fathers, ſo that they were of one ſtock, proceeding from the ſame An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cectors, and were called Brethren, or Nephews, as Kinſmen are, and not by one Father, as <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Iſhmael</hi> was, and by naturall generation of the ſame Parent; a true diſtinction of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118754:6"/> diſcent, apparant for that falſe and fooliſh Court of <hi>Probates</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: yet behold faithfull <hi>Abraham,</hi> Gen. 25. who had nine Children by <hi>Keturah</hi> another Wife, beſides <hi>Iſhmael</hi> whom <hi>Hagar</hi> the <hi>Egyptian, Sarahs</hi> handmaide, bare unto <hi>Abraham;</hi> And to avoide ſtrife, diſcord, contention and diſcenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that might have come or riſen amongſt them as Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, becauſe of the heritage; <hi>Abraham</hi> gave all that he had unto <hi>Iſaack,</hi> But unto the other ſonnes, <hi>Abraham</hi> gave Gifts, and ſent them away from <hi>Iſaac</hi> his ſon, while he yet li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; Ask Dr. <hi>Walker</hi> of (many words) if this be not <hi>Civill Law,</hi> and God ſaid to <hi>Iſaac,</hi> Gen. 26. That <hi>Abraham</hi> obeyed his voice, and kept his Charge, and his Commandements, his Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes and his Laws, and when men degenerated from God, and did not walk as faishfull <hi>Abraham</hi> had done, Then God ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a Law, That the Eldeſt ſonne, or the firſt-born ſonne, by the firſt Wife ſhall be by the father acknowledged for his firſt-born, by the Fathers giving him a double Portion, of all that he hath, for that he is the begining of his ſtrength, the right of the firſt born-ſhip is his, <hi>Deutr.</hi> 21.15, 16, 17. This is Gods law, Maugre corrupt long breath'd Lawyers, or pretended <hi>Regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors</hi> of the Abuſes of <hi>Practiſers</hi> in the Law, or any ſilly Vilaines, or Civilians belonging to <hi>Doctors Commons,</hi> either <hi>Dyers, Fiſhers,</hi> or Lyers of any Court whatſoever, or of that Arbitrary, and ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regular Court of <hi>Probates,</hi> who act and practiſe under the title of Wiſe men or Fools, and who act againſt the Truth, and leave the Law of God, and right of Engliſh Law practiſed in other Courts, purpoſely to deſtroy, by combination, or corrupt will, the right of a firſt-born ſonne, and a legall ſole Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor lawfully admitted, ſworne and made; ſuch muſt either have no knowledge, and then uncapable of being either Judges, Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, or Practiſers therein, or Diſſemblers therein; And <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> ſaith, <hi>He that diſſembleth hatred with lying lipps, and he that inventeth ſlander, is a fool,</hi> Pr. 10.18. And it will, I doubt, not but be agreed on, that he was wiſer then ever (Dr. <hi>Wiſe-man</hi>) And ſuch wicked Lyers, Lawyers, Fiſhers, Wiſemen and Dyers, in any Court whatſoever; who ſlander men by misinformations in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118754:7"/> Court, as you know ſenſibly by your means and contrivance was fooliſhly and malitiouſly, by you and your Compl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for above two years, before you brought about your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binated ends and Purpoſes againſt me, which you may all be aſhamed of, or whoſoever hath done un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ighteouſly in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and judgeth not what is right, as well as in paſſing the Seale, as <hi>Serle Zanchy,</hi> or <hi>Cottle,</hi> to do any wrong, ſuch ought by Law to make ſatisfaction to the Partie that is dammaged, as I ſhall prove yet in this Epiſtle, which act as the Lawyers and <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> of old, which Chriſt rebuked, it will reach alſo the baſe practiſe of Lawyers in our times, either <hi>Chancery men</hi> or <hi>Common Lawyers,</hi> as well as <hi>Civill Lawyers,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be Eccleſiaſticks or Lay-men, and did any Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks fit there more then Mr. <hi>Hugh Peters</hi> in the Court of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates,</hi> it would reach them alſo; I dare ſay, he will not deny it if he were asked, they doing as the Lawyers, and Scribes and Phariſees did, if you compare, <hi>Matt.</hi> 23.2 3, 4. with <hi>Luke</hi> 11.39.42, 43, 44, 45, 46. if they Act and do like them, hypocrittically and unrighteouſly; for I hope he will not deny the Scripture, which ſaith thus, <hi>They did lade men, or Peoples ſhoulders;</hi> and it is underſtood, their Eſtates alſo, <hi>with burdens grievous to be borne:</hi> they being as <hi>rotten graves,</hi> that appear not, into which men ſinke, and are caught of them, before they are aware of them, they being full of ravenning and wickedneſſe, and will not touch the burdens with one of their fingers, they layed then upon the Peoples ſhoulders; And I finding it thus recorded, <hi>Matt.</hi> 23.1. That Chriſt ſpake it, unto the multitude of People, as well as to his Diſciples, when he was upon the Earth with a multitude of woes, which he pronounced againſt them for their Hypocriſy rottenneſſe, oppreſſions, extortions and injuſtice, as well as diſſimulation, and faire ſpeakings and promiſes to the People, which they never intended (which is the ground of Hypocriſie) In the Bibles of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Roman</hi> letter, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted 1609. and 1610. by the Kings Printer <hi>Robert Barker,</hi> as you may read, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.10. The Prophet in his dayes complaining of the fraude, rapine, tyranny, and all kinde of wrong which
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118754:7"/> worldly men then uſed, or wicked men, or Hypocrites, amongſt the reſt of their pretended Vertues, ſaith the Scripture; He crou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth, and boweth: therefore heapes of the poor do fall by his might; and in the Margent it is thus Printed, <hi>By the Hypocriſie of thoſe that have Authority, the Poor are devoured.</hi> And Chriſt warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the People, as well as his own Deciples, that they ſhould not do after their works, but whatſoever they did bid him ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, all thoſe things they were to obſerve, and doe; ſure then they were exact teachers, though bad performers, or doers; But Chriſt ſaid, <hi>All their Works they do for to be ſeen of men,</hi> Matt. 23.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7. They loved the chief ſeat in the Sinagogues, and the uppermoſt place at Feaſts, and to be called, by Titles of Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, and to be ſaluted, honoured, or greeted, in publique pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as if they were ſomewhat more then other men, as many do now in our dayes, but for loving of theſe things, and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing over judgement, and the Love of God, Chriſt pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth woe againſt them, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.42, 43, 44. <hi>Mark</hi> 12.36. (which <hi>Luke</hi> ſaid or ſpake by the Holy Ghoſt,) and without doubt theſe Hypocrites carried themſelves, as cloſe, and covertly, and ſeeming courteous, with as faire and plauſible Pretences as any do now, and as now, ſo then they would compaſſe both Sea and Land for their own ends, to make a Proſilite, and to bring him to beleeve with them, and to be of their Synagogue, though thereby, when he was brought to their belief, he was made twofold more the childe of Hell; by being made one of the Synagogue of Satan; this <hi>Christ</hi> ſpake, <hi>Matt.</hi> 23.15. Who was greater then <hi>Solomon, Luke</hi> 11.31. And as he left it both to Rebuke, and inſtruct that generation, I deſire this pretended wiſe generation, would take notice thereof in this day that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to our Peace, and not to delight to burden their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threns ſhoulders, and to betray their fellow brethren, and their Eſtates; for as <hi>Paul</hi> whom Chriſt counted Faithfull, became in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious no more, and perſecuted none of his Brethren, after he had obtained mercy himſelf. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 12, 13. and was called, and made to beleeve, he averreth <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.2, 3, 4. that every man ſhould pleaſe his Neighbour to edification; as it is written, <hi>The
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118754:8"/> rebuke of them that rebuke thee fell on mee;</hi> for ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> by the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Whatever things are written afore time, are written for our learning, that we through patience,</hi> and comfort of the Scriptures might have <hi>hope;</hi> And ſaith <hi>Paul, They are written for our admonition, upon whom the ends of the Wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ld are come,</hi> 1. Cor. 10.11. Yet he adviſeth, to rebuke them that ſin before all, that others alſo may fear; if it can be proved by two or three Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes; yea, though he were in place, partiallity ſhould not be uſed. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.19, 20, 21. And <hi>Paul</hi> ſhunned not to declare all the <hi>Councell of God,</hi> and he thereby ſtood pure from the blood of all men. <hi>Acts</hi> 20.26, 27. Now this being an Epidemicall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe in <hi>England,</hi> and perticularly rooted in you <hi>(John Burt)</hi> as by Witneſſes will be proved; ſo that it is in you gangrened I fear, or ſetled; you having been the chief plotter, and Acter and Contriver all along againſt me; and Concealer &amp; Decliner, and Inſtigator, and Importunator of all Perſons, of all ſorts, and in all Places; ſo that it is feared, you being m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed therein, may be ſaid, <hi>To have ſpoken Lies in hypocriſie; and have your Conſcience ſeared with a hot-iron;</hi> as the Holy Spirit ſpake by <hi>Paul</hi> expreſly; <hi>In the latter times ſome ſhould depart from the Faith, and ſhould doe.</hi> 1 Tim. 4.1, 2. Therefore this Epiſtle is ſent to rebuke you, that you may not be deſtroyed; and that I may be pure from your blood, and from the blood of all men; and any that are concerned with you herein; Wherefore I inſtruct you with meekneſſe, and intreat you to examine your ſelf; and to judge your own ſelf, for theſe enormities by you acted &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted; that you no longer harden your heart and braze your forehead, and continue in your ſines againſt the Light of <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>Conſcience,</hi> or light of <hi>Nature,</hi> though you ſerved much time of an Aprentiſhip to a <hi>Scrievener;</hi> but as the Apoſtle S. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> by the Holy Spirit adviſeth. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1, 2. <hi>Laying aſide all malice, and all guile, and Hypocriſies, and envyings, and evill ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; As new-born Babes deſire the ſinceer milk of the Word, that you may grow thereby;</hi> for holy <hi>David</hi> through his temptations and experience, could tell you, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.9. <hi>Wherewithall ſhall a young man cleanſe his way? by taking heed thereto, according to thy Word;</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:118754:8"/> for the Prophecie came not in old time by the will of man: But holy men of God ſpake, as they were moved by the holy Ghoſt, 2 <hi>Peter.</hi> 1.21. Wherefore <hi>John Burt</hi> be inſtructed thereby, that you may be recovered out of the ſnare of the Devil, who are taken Captive by him at his will, if God peradventure will give you repentance to the acknowledging of the truth, as it is written, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.25, 26. Therefore in all meekneſſe I again adviſe you to repent, of your many and perticular unfaithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, malitiouſneſſes, envyings, lyings, unnaturall combina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, concealements, threatnings, impriſonings by your ſelf and other your Complices, and falſe reports to ſtop and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine my monies, due to me, not onely 66. l. 13. s. 4 d. in your own hand, beſides the uſe, which is of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Mmrgage of the Red <hi>Lyon</hi> Inn at St. <hi>Edmonds Burie,</hi> but in oth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r mens alſo, to put me to charges in Law-ſuits; <hi>viz.</hi> In <hi>Henry Woods</hi> hand, my Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, which this is the third time, and in <hi>John Wests</hi> hand 60. l. which had been paid me but for you and your Complices, <hi>Jan</hi> 23 1654. beſides my many loſſes other ways, well known to your ſelf, as alſo your contrived Demurrings in <hi>Chancery,</hi> and halfe perjuries, And your cancelling, like a Scrievener with one eare, and detaining ſeverall Writings, as well as much mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys, which belong to me, as the Image and repreſentor of our Fathers Perſon, and your many Provocations, and incitements, as well as inticements of others, to lie and ſweare falſly againſt me, and to ſue me in ſeverall Courts, or to withſtand my right, to cauſe me to ſue for it, to which I was not onely bound in 500. l. to you, with Articles to diſcover our Fathers Eſtate, before letters of Adminiſtration were delivered me in Sir <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaeel Brents</hi> time, but alſo bound to the Prerogative Court with ſecuritie in a farr greater ſum, and ſworn therein alſo to be a faithfull Adminiſtrator to our d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ceaſed Fathers Eſtate, you having ever ſince vexed both my ſelf and others, and then, and ſtill threatning them if they Pay me; and ſuch whom you have, and ſtill do procure with you ſo to doe; alſo your home-ſwearings Perſonally in two Courts. <hi>Viz.</hi> the one of <hi>Chancery,</hi> which I hope in time will be made to ſubmit to the fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118754:9"/> Power of that Ordinance, which was Ordered by His Highneſs the Lord Protector, and his Council to be Printed and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, <hi>Auguſt</hi> 22, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>654. both for their limitation and regulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it ſeeming to be the diſtribution of his own Conſcience therein, and a great ſtep to reform abuſes, though by thoſe ſons of <hi>Zerviah,</hi> which ſure are but as a ſpot in a Pavement, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the whole Nation, it was never yet obeyed, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted unto, and all other Ordinances that have been made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, are eſtabliſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d and compelled to be obeyed by all People under the Power; And alſo your home ſwearing in that Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, Irregulated, unlimmited, and unparralell'd Court of <hi>Probates,</hi> the very Peſt, and Plague, as it is, and hath been lately uſed to this <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation; which I hope the preſent Power will curbe, and bring into Order alſo in due time, and ſettle them by Orders, as the other Courts are ſetled by the Judges of the Land, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Common Pleas</hi> and the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper Bench,</hi> which ſhall be by them publiſhed in Print, as the Ordinance for <hi>Chancery,</hi> for the Peoples inſtructions and relief, and alſo Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their unlimmitted and exceſſive Fees therein taken, as it formerly was by Statute Law, and give them Rules alſo to proceed therin, that for future, as ſaith the <hi>Chancery</hi> Ordinance, that there be no more juſt complaints from the People, ſo that they have declared both the Proceeding and Fees of the <hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery</hi> to be unconſcionable, I appeal to all that have had to do therein, if they have not found it ſo, without they have been in ſpeciall favour in that Court, and then by conſent much may be done; My <hi>Appeal</hi> formerly againſt it, hath ſet forth the iniquity thereof ſufficiently, printed 1653. a Moneth after the Parliament was diſſolved; I read in a Book called, <hi>The Mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of Juſtices,</hi> made by <hi>Henry Horne. pag.</hi> 293. That the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people called the <hi>Chancery,</hi> then a Court of Conſcience, and the Author ſaith, it is to be noted in reſpect of other Courts, the Court of <hi>Chancery</hi> is a Court of a high nature; And the Ordinance made by His Highneſſe, &amp;c. 1654, calls it <hi>The High Court of Chancery,</hi> which <hi>Octob.</hi> 22. 1654. ſhould have taken place for the regulating and limmiting their exceſſive Fees, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118754:9"/> exorbitant practiſes; to the end all Proceedings touching re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief in Equitie to be given to that Court, may be with leſſe trouble, expence and delay then heretofore; thus the <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance</hi> declareth, <hi>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lio</hi> 495 523 unto which all honeſt <hi>Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> ſhould gladly ſhout, <hi>Amen, Amen, Amen,</hi> and which the pen-man hereof hopes to ſee put in execution by His Highn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſs comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd, &amp;c. as ſure, as 44 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſtices, who were hanged in one year, for oppreſſing the People by falſe Judgement, <hi>Mirrour of Juſtices, pag.</hi> 239. that famous law-Book ſaith, <hi>It is an abuſe of the Common-Law, that Justices and their Officers, who kill People by falſe Judgement he not deſtroyed as other murderers,</hi> which King <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred</hi> cauſed to be done; who cauſed 44. Juſtices in one year to be hanged, as murderers for their falſe Judgements, which Judges are in the following Pages, perticularly named, and their falſe and Arbitrary Judgements, for which they ſuff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>red, death or impriſonment, or wounding, or loſſe of limbe or member; And accordingly, he cauſed mortall rewards to cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minall Judges, for wrongfull mortall Judgements, and ſo he did for wrongfull Judgemenss venialls, Impriſonments, for wrongfull impriſonments, and like for like, with the other puniſhments, <hi>pag.</hi> 244. It is an abuſe of the <hi>Common Law,</hi> to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey the Judge who is appealed of doeing wrong, <hi>pages</hi> 158. 230. And the Penman hereof Appealeth from the falſe and wrongfull Judgement of <hi>Thomas Manby, George C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ck, Anthony Kous, John Hild<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſly, Joachim Mathewes,</hi> or all, or any other Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of the Court of <hi>Probates,</hi> and granting Adminiſtrations unto the <hi>Common Law</hi> of the Land, for relief herein, having by Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters forewarned them ſeverall times, that they could not doe it without my conſent, being perſonally preſent and it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily beleeved, ſome of theſe Judges, would think it judgement contrary to Law, and ſo wrongfull and falſe Judg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ment, if they ſhould have ſtood in my place, and others ſhould have ſitten in their places, and ſhould have ſo done by them, and judged contrary to Gods Law, and <hi>Englands</hi> Law, as they have done by me, who have given yon <hi>John Burt</hi> my yonger B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>other by the ſecond ventor, Letters of Adminiſtration, two years
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118754:10"/> after the law had poſſeſſed me thereof, lawfully, and that I had paid, in portions, &amp; taken receits from your ſelf, and you had denyed it in Court, had not our ſiſter perſonally teſtified the ſame againſt you, ſhee ſeeing you receive a part thereof, and her ſelf about that time which was about 18 Moneths ſince, given me a releaſe on her part, which being produced in Court, you having ſeduced her, and by that means defrauded both of us as yet of our parts of 200. l. in your hand, and you villanouſly would have had her to have denyed it as her Act and Deed, and the Judges of <hi>Probates,</hi> &amp;c. would have perſwaded me to have relinqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſhed it, I am ſure you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Dr. <hi>Wiſeman</hi> can rem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mber this, who mis-informed the Judges for you about it ſeverall times, and ſputtered hard therein againſt me then perſonally relating the truth unto the Judges againſt both his and your lies, and your P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>octers alſo <hi>Fiſher</hi> my <hi>Proctor,</hi> either being by you, or ſome of you ſo corrupted, or by others conjured to be dumb in my caſe, that in my abſence you and you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces might attain your intended ends, to null the Adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Son and Heire, as the ſeverall Orders in Court will yet teſtifie, which were commonly drawne by <hi>Dyer</hi> your <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor</hi> to ſpeak as that Viper would have them, who made the Regiſter enter, or ſigne what he pleaſed; thus would you and your <hi>Complices</hi> have caſt out the ſonne long ſince, to have ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the inheritance, and yet he had the Power legally, and was m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de ſole Adminiſtrator of all that was his Fathers Deceaſed, and had long before brought in a true and perfect Inventory, and an Account &amp; Aditionall, which the Order of the Court ſaith, the Judges allowed of <hi>June</hi> 6. 1653. for a true and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect account, as is therein declared, and your Oath alſo then taken, which you may be heartily ttoubled for; and had you one dram of grace, you would, but at laſt you procured an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt Ord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r and upon that, a falſe and wrongfull Judgement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt mee, <hi>viz.</hi> That my Letters of Adminiſtration ſhould be null, and that <hi>John Burt</hi> ſhould have Letters of Adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and it was given you, of which wrongfull Proceedings of the Judges of <hi>Probates,</hi> I have heard Learned men, and Aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118754:10"/> Practiſers both of <hi>Common</hi> and <hi>Civill Laws,</hi> ſay that it was irregularly and illegally done againſt both the <hi>Civill</hi> and the <hi>Common Law,</hi> And that if ſuch Arbitrary Judgements, or Sentences be ſuffered to be Decreed, what <hi>Engliſh man</hi> can ſay he hath any thing his owne, or any inheritance, by <hi>Enliſh Law,</hi> when Judges without the Peoples or Parties conſent, ſhall g ve the title, right, intereſt, dignitie or Eſtate or Inherritance of the People or any perticular Perſon, or p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oprietie thereunto, away from him or them wilfully againſt Law, and contrary to Law; And when Judges do paſſe their ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſdiction, or the bounds of their Delegacies, or of their Commiſſions, and I dare jeopard my life to prove Mr. <hi>Manby</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>Judges,</hi> who gave you Letters of Adminiſtration, have paſſed their juriſdiction and Delegation, and Commiſſion; And for ſuch offences, King <hi>Alfred</hi> did not meddle with the judgements; In l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſer Off nces he did not meddle with judgements, but disinherrited the <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices,</hi> and removed them according to the points of thoſe Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes in all points, where he could underſtand that they had paſſed their juriſdiction, or the bounds of their Delegacy, or of their Commiſſions; or had releaſed or increaſed any puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment contrary to Law, or done any other wrong, in diſſalow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of a reaſonable Exception of the Parties, or to the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Mirrour of Justices, pag.</hi> 245. It is worth the obſerving, and declaring alſo, that the <hi>Judges</hi> of <hi>Probates,</hi> &amp;c. could not be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of my Caſe, and rightfull Cauſe, it having been d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding (though to my grief and loſſe) as long as Mr. <hi>Manby</hi> or Mr. <hi>Cock</hi> had been in and out of Commiſſion, by Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or Ordinance ſince, although I had beleeved that I had ended <hi>Septmeber</hi> the 28. before the Acted grew vacatt or null, <hi>October</hi> the firſt, 1653. and by the Order of the Court I had char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges given me, though ſince, by ſome Officers, and my own <hi>Proctor,</hi> I have been very much abuſed, untill he diſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nted, and denyed to own my buſineſſe any longer for that in op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n Court I had demanded judgem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt againſt him for conſenting againſt me, and abuſing me, and labouring to deſtroy me; ſo that ſo much as the <hi>Judges</hi> hath heard, not onely from my ſelf in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118754:11"/> Court pleaded in Faylor of my <hi>Proctor,</hi> but alſo by that juditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Advocate, and Auntient Practiſer, Honored Dr. <hi>Swett,</hi> and ſeverall Letters and Petitions to enable th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ir memories, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall exceptions in writeing delivered them, to keep off falſe and wrongfull judgement; for in the <hi>Mirrour of Juſtices, pag.</hi> 198. It is ſaid, <hi>The Judge doth not offend ſo much, that he doth not make the Law, but he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffendeth in fooliſh undertaking upon him to judge fooliſhly, or falſly;</hi> And when you had buried me in <hi>Ludgate,</hi> in the height of your Malice and Rage, as one d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad, or not in being to appear in my own right, and my <hi>Proctor</hi> deſented, and the <hi>Judges</hi> denying me any <hi>Proctor</hi> in Court to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſiſt me, or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear for me, or to anſwer for me in my abſenſe, I ſent my Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from <hi>Ludgate, December</hi> the 8. 1654, Which Mr. <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mas El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis</hi> brought them, which was read in Court, and the par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined by the then <hi>Judges,</hi> if it were mine, written by me or no; And I ſent it as a Meſſenger, who came to them from the dead in Priſon, to warn and Proteſt againſt them, as often I had done before, that they ſhould not dare to do unrighteouſly in judgement, who ſeemed then to be much minded to give you Letters of Adminiſtration, which Originall Letter, of which that was a Copy, is ſtill to be ſeen, and as <hi>Cain</hi> churliſhly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed the Lord, who inquired for <hi>Abel</hi> whom he had ſlaine, ſo I, though ſhut up by you, cryed by my Letter to the <hi>Judges</hi> of <hi>Probates,</hi> that as I was the Eldeſt ſonne of our Father Deceaſed, and ſole adminiſtrator and repreſentor of his Perſon, that they would do no wrongfull judgement then unto me, though I, was incloſed and ſhut up as a dead man, and in that Letter, I did averre, as I had done before in Court in <hi>March,</hi> 1654. when I put in my Exceptions to the <hi>Proctors</hi> Abbortive and miscon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived report which was underwritten thus; Mr. <hi>Manby,</hi> I doe averre that my life, Libertie or Eſtate cannot be taken away, but where the Law doth it, and it was but the other day, the Lord Protector took an Oath, <hi>That he would Govern according to the Laws, Statutes and Cuſtomes of this Nation</hi> (and the deſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a Court ought not to be contrary to Law and Reaſon.)
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118754:11"/> thus teſtifies <hi>Nathanael Burt,</hi> and this was added to my Letter alſo from <hi>Ludgate</hi> to teſtifie they were the lines of a living man, though the Judges, with you and your Compli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cs looked upon me as dead, in your judgements, and practiſes, and this Letter alſo is preſerved to be given in teſtimony agai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt their unrighteouſn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſe and falſe wrongfull judgement, and your frawd and maliciouſneſſe; <hi>John Burt</hi> herein may be read, you have put me to no ſmall trouble, loſſes and attendances, and charges in ſeverall Courts, beſides Impriſonments alſo by you and your Complices combination, to deſtroy me in my Name, Liberty, Eſtate, dependencie of Trade, to gain bread the ſtaffe of life in this Orbe, to make me fall under you, who am the Survior of our deceaſed Fathers Perſon in Law, and lively re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent or thereof, and thus you and your Complices have Act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to keep me from an Account of the Eſtate of my deceaſed Father, who am in Law the ſole Adminiſtrator to his Eſtate, and all parts and particulars thereof, and to detaine and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal from me, and to turn it to your own uſe, profit and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit; Witneſſe that concealing of one Hundred Pounds of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, our Father ſent to one <hi>William Whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtone</hi> of St. <hi>Giles Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burn,</hi> about the year 1638, or 1639. of which, the uſe was ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly paid unto our Father, untill the Chriſtmaſs before he dyed, as by his Book under his own hand will appear, and by witneſſe alſo, four Pounds half yearly, which was ſecured to him, his Executors, Adminiſtrators and Aſſignes by a Mort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage of two ſeverall Houſes in <hi>Holburne,</hi> held by Leaſe from one <hi>William Wooley</hi> Eſq of <hi>Lincolnſhire,</hi> which Writeings of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyance, &amp; ſecurity, you poſſeſſed your ſelf of ſecretly &amp; frau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulently, as you did of our Fathers Keyes out of his pocket in his lifetime, to his great grief, and vexation, he wanting much of his tongues benefit to expreſſe, but not then quite dumbe, which you took advantage of, and by this meanes poſſeſſed your ſelf of ſeverall Moneys and other Writeings of Bonds and Mortgages, which you kept concealed, and ſome ſince Cancelled, and others you received the uſe and profits there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of your ſelf, ſometime uncancelled, and you knowing my Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118754:12"/> was in Power and in full force, which will be made to appear; And at the ſame time in the <hi>Chancery,</hi> to my firſt Bill, you and your Complices generally demurr and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and not long after to my ſecond Bill for diſcoverie onely againſt your ſelf, you ſweare poſitively an untruth to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor part of our Fathers Eſtate, concealed by you; and alſo of the Mortgage of 200. l. of St. <hi>Edmonds Burie;</hi> ſomewhat there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you confeſſe, upon which confeſſion, it was Ordered to be devided as 200. l. of cleer Eſtate, of which you know the moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie or Third part belongeth to me, and as much unto our ſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers Children, ſhe being deceaſed ſince, and you having paid neither of us, and though it was put in my Inventory, yet you know it never came out of your hands, though it came to my knowledge, and I had been forſworne, and had forfeited a Bond of 500. l. to you, had I not diſcovered it as part of our Fathers Eſtate, he having entred it into his Book with his own hand writing, which you and others have ſeen, and you your ſelf cannot deny, which in the Court of <hi>Probates,</hi> &amp;c. before the Judges, you confeſſed in my preſence, you canceled; ſaying <hi>Samuel Thomlins (once your fervant) could teſtifie it was given you;</hi> which you know, you then, and in your <hi>Anſwer</hi> lyed in, for he hath denyed it unto your face, as alſo <hi>in his Anſwer in Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery;</hi> But this <hi>Mortgage</hi> of Mr. <hi>Whetſtones,</hi> which you knew of <hi>many years belore,</hi> of 100. l. paying 8. l <hi>a year,</hi> this is ſo ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and <hi>Concealed</hi> and <hi>Forſworn</hi> the knowledge of by You in both <hi>Courts</hi> of <hi>Chancery</hi> &amp; <hi>Probates,</hi> yet you know you received of Mr. <hi>William Whetſtone</hi> the ſon of <hi>William Whetſtone</hi> deceaſed, who was bound with his Father upon the old <hi>Mortgage</hi> to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form <hi>Covenants,</hi> after the rate of 8 <hi>per Cent.</hi> after our Fathers deceaſe, I having Letters of Adminiſtration, and that you had bound your ſelf to me <hi>in</hi> 500. l. <hi>Bond, with Articles, to diſcover our deceaſed Fathers Eſtate,</hi> which <hi>Bond</hi> you know (if this be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved) is forfeited by you: And thus you <hi>concealed</hi> the ſame as all the reſt, And it is beleeved, <hi>you have concealed a Bond of a</hi> 100. l. <hi>for the payment of</hi> 50. l. wherin <hi>Jeames Ryton,</hi> and one <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bias Markeham</hi> &amp; old Mrs. <hi>Ryton</hi> were <hi>Bound to our Father, and it
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118754:12"/> is entred into his Book,</hi> the uſe received by him about Chriſtmaſs before he deceaſed, with his own hand, as Mr. <hi>Whetstones</hi> is, and demanding of Mrs. <hi>Ryton</hi> to be ſatisfyed therein, the ſame day Mr. <hi>Whetstone</hi> had ſatisfied me the truth of his; ſhe ſord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly denyed ever that ſhe knew of any Bond given our Father, or any money had of him, as though you had been in her belly to prompt her to lie in her Anſwer; and ſo ſoon as ſhe had done ſpeaking, <hi>James Ryton</hi> appeared, and he being demanded con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning 50. l. he ſhould be bound for with one <hi>Markham</hi> and his Mother, he before her face confeſſed it, and hath not yet given me full ſatisfaction of payment thereof, and to whom; Now ſince you ſware ſo deſperately, and <hi>Whetſtones</hi> conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment having lyen ſo ſnugg, I ſee that neither <hi>Lies</hi> nor <hi>Oathes</hi> will choak you, for it will be proved, that you have received the uſe to your ſelf, upon the old Mortgage for time alſo after our father deceaſed; and afterwards in Mr. <hi>Waltons</hi> houſe, the Scrievener or ſhop you then ſealed new Writings in your own Name, with Mr. <hi>Whetſtone,</hi> the ſurvivor of his deceaſed Father, &amp; then you alſo with him, and in his Preſence altered the old property thereof into your own Name, and then cancelled the Old Writings, and Bonds made between both our Fathers de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed as before related, which were at 8. l. <hi>per Cent.</hi> and yet you like a well-tutered Scrieveners bratt, in all this you well knew you had acted, and done, ſware you knew nothing of this belonging to your Fathers Eſtate; And after you had can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celled theſe old Writings and the Bond thereto belonging; as is before mentioned, and will be proved to be true to your face, and to your ſhame, which by the old men deceaſed, had been made and ſealed, and again renewed them in your owne Name, with his ſonne <hi>William Whetſtone,</hi> you could not reſt content therewith, and ſatisfied; But you muſt have them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered again by Mr. Walton, And then you doe intitle and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt one <hi>Francis Rich</hi> in the ſaid renewed Mortgage, pretending to Mr. <hi>Whetſtone</hi> you had received of <hi>Francis Rich,</hi> for the ſaid Mortgage of his not long before you had renewed in your own Name, though fraudulently, as he now beleeveth, 100. l in
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118754:13"/> money, for which cauſe ſay you, and <hi>Walt n</hi> the Scrievener, <hi>Whetſtone</hi> muſt now aſſigne to <hi>Francis Rich,</hi> and become bound to pay the Uſe to him, as they had done to our Father for 14. years before, and to you for ſome time; Then after ſealing, to <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch</hi> by <hi>Whetſtone,</hi> there is a ſuite commenced, or brought in the Exchequer of <hi>Pleas</hi> againſt <hi>William Whetſtone,</hi> in the Name of <hi>Francis Rich;</hi> and in <hi>Michaelmas</hi> Terme, 1654. recovery is made againſt <hi>Whetstone</hi> in the ſaid ſuite, and <hi>Whetstone</hi> is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by forced to compond the ſame, and pay charges in <hi>Francis Rich</hi> his Name, who is now of opinion neither <hi>John Burt,</hi> or <hi>Francis Rich</hi> had or hath any right or intereſt therein, and alſo <hi>William Whetstone</hi> at that time Judgement being in the Name of <hi>Francis Rich</hi> obtained againſt him, or to be, was forced to promiſe payment thereof to <hi>Francis Rich,</hi> and for his uſe, as then he could agree to ſtop Execution, and accordingly he paid 25. l. of the ſaid 100 l. <hi>January</hi> 4. 1654. and all Intereſt unto that preſent day, beſides charges of ſuite therein, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to promiſe, Twenty Five Pounds from the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly, untill he had paid in <hi>Francis Rich</hi> his Name, and for his uſe, the full ſum of one Hundred Pounds, and Mr. <hi>Whetſtone</hi> ſaith, In all his life as yet, he never did ſee or know the ſaid <hi>Francis Rich,</hi> and this he ſpake Thurſday the 29th of <hi>March,</hi> 1656. but ſaid, <hi>Thomas Walton</hi> the Scrievener had been there to ſee if 25.l. in money were ready to be paid in his Name, and for his uſe; and <hi>William Whetſtone</hi> ſaith, He paid the 25.l. above meneioned unto <hi>John Burt,</hi> and the Intereſt, in the Preſence of <hi>Thomas Walton,</hi> and took his Receipt for <hi>Francis Rich</hi> his uſe, and that he had not ſo much as ever known <hi>Nathanael Burt</hi> the elder Brother of <hi>John Burt,</hi> and ſole Adminiſtrator of <hi>Nathanael Burt</hi> their Father deceaſed, untill <hi>March</hi> following after, and beleeveth, if he had known the Adminiſtrator, He ſhould not have payed <hi>John Burt</hi> any money, or ſuffered the Old Writings to have been altered in his Name, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards into <hi>Riches</hi> name, or agreed to the cancelling the old Writings. Oh <hi>John Burt,</hi> heare <hi>Pauls</hi> advice, which was inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by God, if you will not hear me, who ſaith, <hi>Ephe.</hi> 5.25.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:118754:13"/> 
               <hi>Wherefore, cast off lying,</hi> or <hi>putting away lying, and ſpeak every man truth unto his Neighbour;</hi> See <hi>Eſay.</hi> 30.1.8.12.15 <hi>For wee are members one of another; and the Lord, the Holy One of Iſrael hath cauſed it to be noted in a Book, that it may be for the time to come for ever and ever:</hi> which you may read <hi>Prov.</hi> 12 19.22. &amp; 15.27, 28, 29, 20.21.21.6.28.24, <hi>Lying lips are an abomination to the Lord, But they that deale truly are his delight, But a lying tongue is but for a moment; He that is greedy of gaine, troubleth his own Howſe: and he that maketh haſte to be rich, ſhall not be innocent;</hi> An Inher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance may begotten haſtily at the beginning: but the end thereof ſhall not be bleſſed; And I beleeve, in time, if you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive not this inſtruction, many more of your Concealements and frauds, you have ſo luſtily covered with Lying; and ſo falſly ſworn againſt, of which you ſee this apparently is one, for a righteous man hateth Lying, but a wicked man is loathſom, and commeth to ſhame. <hi>Prov.</hi> 13.5. and <hi>whoſo robbeth his Father, or his Mother, and ſaith it is no tranſgreſſion, the ſame is the Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of a deſtroyer.</hi> And you robbed our Father of his Keyes in his life time, which you know too well, which the Citie <hi>Cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> cryed before your door about ſeven Weekes before he dyed, though you never delivered them no more then the Leaſe of the Crown you poſſeſſed, and the <hi>Fine</hi> thereto belonging, and much Monies &amp; other Bonds &amp; Mortgages, and money belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then to him, and ſince to his Eſtate; All which hath been denyed by you in <hi>Chancery,</hi> by your delaying, hum—haw <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murrer,</hi> and in your <hi>Anſwer</hi> alſo. Yet <hi>John,</hi> you may very well remember, you once had me to one Mr. <hi>Oglethorps</hi> in <hi>Alderman-Bury;</hi> I could name you the day alſo, for I entred it for Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, who is Attorney of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper Bench,</hi> and then ſaid, you would deny your <hi>Demurrer,</hi> and give an <hi>Anſwer</hi> to my firſt Bill in <hi>Chancery;</hi> if I would accept thereof, which it ſeemeth he then hindred you in, or of, like a kindle-coal, and ſower of diſcord, for this was within Seven Moneths after our Father deceaſed; which had you Anſwered then, you might have ſaved many ſuits in Law, and much Money you have cauſed to be ſpent, and loſs &amp; ſufferings to me, and it is like, have had a conſcience leſs
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118754:14"/> void of offence, but after you were come forth from him, I ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving left you together, you may remember that before you and I then parted, you wept to me, and ſaid, You durſt not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the ſaid Bill, leaſt that you ſhould make your ſelf guilty of Felony thereby, the Keyes of our Father having been Cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and they and other things of our Fathers by you denied, and the God of truth knoweth this is truth, for I beleeve as it is written, <hi>A falſe Witneſs</hi> ſhall not be unpuniſhed, <hi>and he that ſpeaketh</hi> Lies <hi>ſhall periſh, he ſhall not eſcape,</hi> it is mentioned twice in five Verſes. <hi>Prov.</hi> 19.5, 9. <hi>and a lying tongue, An heart that deviſeth wicked imaginations, A falſe Witneſſe that ſpeaketh Lies, and him that ſoweth Diſcord among Brethren,</hi> are foure of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven things God hateth. <hi>Prov.</hi> 6.17, 18, 19. and that are to Him an Abomination; Since it is thus <hi>John Burt,</hi> you muſt repent, for your Lies, ſpoken and ſworne by you in the Court of <hi>Probates,</hi> &amp;c. with your hand lifted up towards heaven, <hi>June</hi> 6. 1653. and in your <hi>Chancery</hi> Anſwer not long after; and obſerve it well, though I do not ſay as <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid when <hi>Ananias</hi> lied, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled, or played the <hi>Hypocrite,</hi> diſcovering a part, and keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing back a part of what he ſold his poſſeſſion for, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.1, 2, 3, 4. <hi>VVhilſt it remained, was it not thy own?</hi> and this was by the Apoſtle called <hi>deceit,</hi> as well as <hi>Hypocriſie,</hi> diſſembling and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; yet you do not onely keep back much of our Fathers E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate and conceal it, and denie it, but you ſweare thereunto, and lye in your ſwearing; and for your ſwearing a Lie; I ſay to you, as <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid to <hi>Ananias, Why hath Satan filled thine heart to lie to the Holy Ghost?</hi> Why haſt thou let Satan fill thine heart to lie in the Preſence of God, with thine hand lifted up towards heaven, as is before ſet forth; The Lord by <hi>Hoſea</hi> ſaith, <hi>By lying and ſwearing, with other ſinnes, a Land is brought to mourne,</hi> and all therein to languiſh, for abuſing of the God of truth; and ſuch wicked ſpeakings, and ſwearings, in Scripture are called as well <hi>Curſings</hi> as <hi>Lyings,</hi> and <hi>Perjurie,</hi> if you read the Bible with Annotations, it is ſaid <hi>Perjurie,</hi> in the other <hi>Curſing.</hi> Pſal. 14.7. <hi>His mouth is full of Curſing and Deceit, and fraud;</hi> ſure he is looked on by <hi>David</hi> to be ſo wicked, that he doth not care
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:118754:14"/> what he deviſeth or doth in his Pride, to bring about his ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined or malitious ends, or what he ſaith or ſweareth; <hi>under his tongue is miſchief and vanity,</hi> Pſal. 50.12. <hi>And let them be taken in their Pride, even for their prrjury and Lies they ſpeake, for the ſinn of their mouth, and the words of their lipps;</hi> And we ſee the <hi>Pillory</hi> catch them ſometimes by the Law of <hi>England,</hi> for their falſe ſwearings, the ſin of their mouth, though in the <hi>Chancery</hi> ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing lipps is cherriſhed, to beget Delayes, and Demurres, and to procure Motion, upon Motion, and Order upon Order, as thouſands by woefull Experience have found, to their great loſs, and detryment, yea to their undoing and impoveriſhing and ruine; For if the Lord had not been on my ſide, long ere this I had been devoured therein: as now the Court of <hi>Probates</hi> deſtroy my <hi>Title</hi> and <hi>Intereſt</hi> againſt Law, to deſtroy and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punge, or draw out my Eſtate in Charge of Law-ſuits to defend my right by Law, even my birth-right, which by Law was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven me, to be ſole Adminiſtrator of my deceaſed Fathe s E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, and of all and ſingular the Goods, Chattells and Debts of the ſaid diſceaſed whatſoever; and the Law gave me power to demand, by my Letters of Adminiſtration, and Collect; Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy and in legall manner, require all, and all manner of debt or debts due and oweing to the ſaid deceaſed; Theſe are part of the words of my Adminiſtration, and I would very fain know of the Judges for <hi>Probates,</hi> and granting Letters of Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if an Adminiſtrator can Demand, Coll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>; Leavy and in a legall manner require, all and all manner of Debt and Debts due &amp; oweing to the ſaid diſceaſed, he is made Adminiſtrator unto, if any, who concealing the major part, or part thereof, leſſer or more, and ſweare the contrary before their faces in Court, as you have done <hi>(John Burt)</hi> and if I or another man, by vertue of Letters of Adminiſtration, can either demand, Leavy, and in a legall manner require, any debt or Debts, or Collect, any ſuch due or owing, he wanting Witneſs thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, ſo long as they continue concealed, buryed, and detained, by the Policie, deceit, fraude, and evill Conſcience or contrivance of the Concealor, who maliciouſly ſweareth &amp; falſly, he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:118754:15"/> not thereof, or of any part of the deceaſeds Eſtate, or parcell th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reof, that any hath come to his hand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> or Poſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſion ſince the deceaſe of the inteſtate, or doth r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>main in his Cuſtody, at his preſent ſwearing, n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ither doth he know of any of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſeds Eſtate, remaining in the hands or P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſeſſion of a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rſon; but onely of the Adminiſtrator <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uch an Oat be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken in any Court of Equity or of <hi>Probates,</hi> by, any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, how the Adminiſtrator can either Collect or Leavy in a legall manner, by any Power of his Adminiſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ation, any Debt o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Debts oweing and due to the ſaid Eſtate, when men will ſo pernitiouſly conceale and combine together to defraude the Adminiſtrator, and ſo curſedly lie, and ſweare therein, untill time diſcover the truth thereof, and that by witneſs to teſtifie the ſame that ſo the obſtinate concealer of the inteſtates Eſtate, which denyeth it by Oathes, and maketh his neck as an Iron ſinew, and his brow Braſſe, to lie, and ſweare untruths, which it is beleeved you have done, for which I pray the Lord, who deferred his anger to the houſe of <hi>Jaacob,</hi> and refrained to cut them off, to give you repentance, that you may no more ſware falſly, and diſhonour the Almighty, by taking his Name in vain; I teſtifie therefore unto you <hi>John Burt,</hi> that by the Law of God, and man, you have no part of our Fathers Eſtate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth in your hands or cuſtody, or diſpoſed of and by you concealed, belongeth to you, or any you have diſpoſed of it unto, without my conſent thereunto, and thereof, for by Gods law, you ought to reſtore it to me as the next of kin, and ſo the repreſentor of his Perſon, or Father diſceaſed, and by law ſole Adminiſtrator of all that can be called his Eſtate, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing thereunto in his life, and at his death, and you knew thereof very well, it being the ſecond Article of our Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>That</hi> Nathanael Burt, <hi>the eldeſt ſonne of</hi> Nathanael Burt <hi>deceaſed, Citizen and Sadler of</hi> London, <hi>ſhould ſue forth of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative Court, under the ſeale of the ſaid Court. Letters of Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration;</hi> and the third Article thereof; <hi>Item,</hi> That either of the ſaid Parties ſhall, and Will from time to time, to the utmoſt of their, and either of their knowledge, make full and cleer
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:118754:15"/> diſcovery, and Declaration of the ſaid Eſtate; and to this you know Major <hi>Hayne</hi> the Scrievener that made them, and his two Servants are witneſſes therein, and at the ſame time you ſealed a Bond of 500. l. to me, to keep the Articles and Covenants therein contained; which was to Diſcover from time, to time, the Eſtate, but not to conceale the Eſtate from time to time, which if you ſubmit not your ſelf for the breach thereof, time may compell you thereunto, or diſcover it to <hi>Englands</hi> Law, which may compell you to perform or ſuffer accordingly; and reward you for breach of your Articles and Covenants, and Bond, and faith, as a younger ſonne, or younger Brother, and then truth will diſcover it to time, and time then will not conceal it from the knowledge of men, when that ſhall come to paſſe: And you and your Complices oppoſed me all that you could, before my <hi>Letters</hi> of <hi>Administration</hi> were ſealed to me and withſtood me to the face to hinder me therein; but then I ſtriking the words of the Statute law, 31 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. 11. and the 21 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.5. And proving my ſelf to be the next of kin, and the next moſt lawfull Freind of our Father, who died inteſtate, and none being in equalitie and degree of kindred with me; which being by me written out of the Book, and brought in my hand, that I might ſtrengthen my Claim thereby, you and your Complices Pride was abated, your malice for the preſent aſſwaged and your Devices for that time confounded, and by Letters of Adminiſtration I was legally confirmed ſole Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrator, &amp;c. and neither you nor your Complices ſecretly or openly could hinder me thereof except you had bereft me of my life, and by that means my <hi>laſt glaſſe had been run,</hi> as in <hi>September</hi> laſt 1644. you threatned me; ſo indeed if you had not ſuffered by law, you might have come to have been Adminiſtrator to our Fathers Eſtate deceaſed; But while I live, you cannot be by Gods Law or <hi>Englands Law,</hi> or <hi>Cuſtome,</hi> for if that there were any truth, or mercy, or knowledge of God in the <hi>Chancery</hi> to be found, I or another man might have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief therein, according to the Statute of the Fift of <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 5. which ſaith, <hi>For the avoiding as well of long and tedious Suites, as
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:118754:16"/> alſo great Expences in proſecuting of Civill Cauſes, by reaſon of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Appeales permited to be made by Order of the Lawes Civill in ſuch caſes,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Be it inacted,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>all and every ſuch Judgement or Sentence definitive, given or pronounced in any Civill and Marine Cauſe, upon Appeal lawfully to be made therein to the Queens Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie in Her Highneſs Court</hi> of <hi>Chancery, by ſuch Commiſſioners,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>as it hath been uſed in ſuch Caſes ſhall be finall, and no further Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to be had or made from the ſaid Judgement or Sentence defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.</hi> I would ask any man, or Commiſſioner thereof, How the People can expect Equitie therein, or relief thereby, ſince they will not obey and fulfill that Equitable and lawdable Ordinance, Ordained by His Highneſſe the Lord <hi>Protector,</hi> by and with the conſent of His Council, who Ordained therein, That the Chancellor, Keeper or Commiſſioners of the <hi>Great Seal</hi> for the time being, ſhall according to the times, and in manner by this Ordinance preſcribed, put in Executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, all the Rules, Lawes, Orders and Directions before menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned; That for the future there be no more cauſe of juſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints from the People, <hi>folio.</hi> 522. 523 or who can or dare be incouraged to appeal to His Highneſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Court of <hi>Chaucery,</hi> while the Practiſers therein delay the People, and put them to ſuch trouble and Expence, that it is ſcarce one of a thouſand, but may feelingly &amp; experimentally ſay; that when they are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining therein, and wayting for Equity, the <hi>Remedy</hi> there is as bad, if not worſe then the <hi>Diſeaſe;</hi> being thus feelingly ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of the iniquitie of this unconſcionable Court, which the Commiſſioners ſhould take care with all diligence and Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpection, that all the Officers, Miniſters, Clerks and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, belonging to the ſaid <hi>Court</hi> do honeſtly, and faithfully &amp;c. in the <hi>Chancery,</hi> but how many faithfull <hi>Engliſh</hi> men hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily deſire the regulation, yea rather the Reformation thereof, in Conſcience, in honeſty and truth and of all Courts of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicature, according to Gods Word, and Law and not that they ſhould imagine and practiſe miſchief in the Law; I conclude againſt the iniquity, Falſhood, and falſe judgements I have ſeen in the <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Chancery,</hi> which when they have ſubmitted
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:118754:16"/> to the Ordinance, I will call the High Court of <hi>Chancery,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they may be then ſaid to be under His Highneſſe Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, when they obey his Ordinances, which are for Gods glory and the Peoples good, as this Ordinance it is hoped, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but be, and alſo that thing ſo irregular, and unlimmittd, at <hi>Doctors Commons,</hi> which calls it ſelf, with all that <hi>rabble Rowt</hi> belongs thereunto, a Court of <hi>Probates,</hi> &amp;c. when ſitting, which formerly ſate in the <hi>Starre Chamber</hi> place at <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> where when there were Biſhops and a King, or a King and Councill and Biſhops, held a Court there, called the <hi>Starre-Chamber</hi> from the place; and it is beleeved by judicious men, though they were cryed but againſt for Injuſtice, Extortion and Opreſſing of the People, and acting Arbitrarily againſt Law, that theſe have exceeded their Exorbitances, and have exacted, and extorted from the People, ſince their being, which was in comparriſon but the other day, abundantly more then they, only theſe have ſome colourableneſs for their exacting of <hi>Fees</hi> by the Act of <hi>Parliament</hi> made <hi>Aprill.</hi> 1653. to continue in force untill the firſt of <hi>Octoher,</hi> 1653. and no longer, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of the <hi>Fees</hi> taken by the <hi>Registers,</hi> their ſallaries, and under Officers being paid, and <hi>Clerks,</hi> the overpluſs or profits to be paid to Commiſſioners for the uſe of the Navy. Reader, I will give you an account of one Extortion Acted in this <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Probates, June</hi> the 8. 1654. by which a Widow with five Children was oppreſſed againſt the <hi>Statute</hi> of the 21 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.5. In my own ſight and knowledge, ſince obtainmed of the Statute Law to curbe their Exactions and Oppreſſions thereof, which was thus; A Miniſter of the Court of <hi>Probates</hi> agreed with the Widdow, before he would deliver her the Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration under the Seal of the Court, for 3. l. for which ſhe paid him down preſently 50. s. and promiſed him 10. s. more, and then he delivered the Widdow Letters of <hi>Adminiſtration,</hi> her Husband dying Inteſtate, and her <hi>Inventory</hi> did but amount to not full 20. l. and by Statute Law, he ſhould have taken but 3 s. 6 d, if they had amounted to 40. l. <hi>sterling,</hi> ſo they had not exceeded, and not above; and I never knew this Statute repeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:118754:17"/> and the unlawfull Exactions are ſaid in the ſaid Act, <hi>To be againſt Right and Juſtice;</hi> and I pray, why hath not His High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs the Lord Protector and His Councill, ſince Parliaments have neglected it, Power to eaſe the People in ſuch unlawfull Exactions of <hi>Fees</hi> as the <hi>Chancery,</hi> and the Court of <hi>Probates</hi> by their Miniſters exacted, Extorted &amp; taken to the great oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on &amp; impoveriſhing of the People; witneſs this diſtreſſed Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows Caſe with five Children, who hath never been able ever ſince to pay that money, where ſhe was faine to borrow it to ſtop this Extorting Miniſters appetite of money, or ſcarcely to put cloathes on her <hi>Children</hi> for ſhift convenient: And <hi>Exacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Extortion</hi> and <hi>Oppreſſion</hi> are forbidden by Gods Law and Word, which People, Officers, Judges and Miniſters of <hi>Courts,</hi> who forſake Gods Law, and Word, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.158. <hi>I beheld the Tranſgreſſors,</hi> ſaith David, <hi>and was grieved, becauſe they kept not thy Word, Rivers of Waters run down mine eyes, becauſe they keep not thy Law.</hi> O that our Governours and People would doe the like: Wherefore hear your <hi>Elder Bro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hers</hi> Exhortation <hi>John Burt,</hi> and ſuffer this my rebuke, for your ſin againſt God, our deceaſed Father, whom you have much abuſed, and belyed, and my ſelf the Pen-man hereof, and alſo your own ſelf, and your malicious ſinning hath now found you out, and in our Fathers life time alſo cauſed him, when you brought your Children, and ſet them up upon his bed-ſide, which ſure was well done of you, that he might bleſſe them before he departed this life, and your ſelf alſo, but he remembring how extreamly you had abuſed him, by poſſeſſing your ſelf of his Keyes, out of his Pocket, which he had perſued you to your owne houſe for, though he were not ſo capable to expreſſe by words, to you, as to reprove ſome, that others as well as your ſelf, might hear him declare himſelf demonſtratively; yet you know hee remembred your ungodly abuſing of him, and therfore would not acknowledge you, or your Children, but did bid you and them be gone, be gone, take them away, take them away, as though the ſight of you and your Children, were both of you a grievous vexation to him, he then extreamly wringing his
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:118754:17"/> hands, and lifting them up ſo, and then ſpreading them, doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling his diſlike, ſaying, <hi>Be gone, be gone, away, away,</hi> to you and your Children, and would not be quiet, whilſt you and your Children were in his preſence; and though you made it your advantage in his Infirmity to Poſſeſſe what you could of his by your over-reaching, and fraudulent and unlawfull deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or deceiving Policie; pray that it may not be your <hi>Curſe</hi> in which you think to <hi>have bleſſed your ſelf;</hi> ſee <hi>Jaacobs</hi> filialneſs, He durſt not offend or abuſe his Father when he was blinde, though his Mother bid him obey her voice therein. <hi>Gen.</hi> 27.8.12. <hi>My Father peradventure will feel me, and I ſhall ſeem to him, as a Deceiver, and I ſhall bring a Curſe upon me, and not a Bleſſing;</hi> And by theſe your treſpaſſes againſt our Father, and my ſelf, you have even almoſt deſtroyed me, your Elder Brother, in my out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward or Temperall Eſtate, God knoweth, by multitudes of Troubles and Loſſes, and Law Suites, and Lawyers Anſwering, with the Money belonging thereto drawn out and expended, the better to colour your guiltineſſe, And I ſhould make my ſelf guilty of all theſe your ſinnes, and Treſpaſſes, If I ſhould not rebuke you; I muſt therefore rebuke you, and that openly, if I will obſerve Gods Commands, and Scripture Rules, For it is written, <hi>Levit.</hi> 19.17. <hi>Thou ſhalt not hate thy Brother in thine heart, but thou ſhalt plainly rebuke him, and not ſuffer ſinne upon him,</hi> ſaith the Margent, <hi>or that thou beare not ſinne for him, thou ſhalt in any wiſe rebuke him;</hi> Wherefore, that you may not bleſs your ſelf in your <hi>evill Wayes,</hi> ſaying, You have not ſinned in all that you have done to our deceaſed Father, and to my ſelf, and to the Eſtate, as is herein related, and charged by me, which you know is truth; See and read what the Lord commanded <hi>Moſes, to teach the People;</hi> which I told you before, are written in a Book for our learning, for the time to come for ever and ever. <hi>Ye ſhall not ſteal, neither deal falſly, neither Lie one to another, And ye ſhall not ſweare by my Name falſly, Thou ſhalt not defraude thy Neighbour, neither rob him,</hi> and reade <hi>Levit.</hi> 6.1, 2, 3, 4, 5. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with <hi>Numb.</hi> 5.6, 7, 8. It is written, <hi>If a ſoul ſin, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit a Treſpaſs againſt the Lord, and lie unto his Neighbour in that
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:118754:18"/> which was delivered him to keep,</hi> or <hi>in fellowſhip,</hi> or <hi>dealing,</hi> ſaith the Margent, or <hi>that which was put to him of truſt,</hi> in a thing <hi>taken away by violence, hath deceived his Neighbour,</hi> or <hi>doth by Robbery or violence oppreſs his Neighbour,</hi> or <hi>hath found that which was loſt, and lyeth concerning it,</hi> &amp; <hi>ſweareth falſly; Or hath found that which was loſt, and denyeth it, and forſweareth it, and ſweareth falſly, in any of all theſe that a man doth, ſinning therein, or for any of theſe things that a man doth, wherein he ſinneth,</hi> Then it ſhall be, becauſe he hath ſinned, and is guilty, or when I ſay, <hi>he thus ſinneth, and treſpaſſeth, that he ſhall restore that which he took violently away, or the thing which he hath deceitfully gotten, or he ſhall then</hi> reſtore <hi>the Robbery that he hath robbed, or the thing by violence which he took by force, or the thing which was delivered him to keep, or the lost thing which he found; Or all that, about which he hath ſworne falſly, Or for whatſoever he hath ſworn falſly, he ſhall even restore it in the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall, and ſhall adde the fift part more thereto, and give it unto him to whom it appartaineth, or he ſhall both restore it in the whole Sum, and give it unto him to whom it pertaineth in the day of his Treſpaſs-Offering,</hi> ſaith the Margent, or <hi>in the day of his being found guilty, or the ſame day he offereth for his Treſpaſs, or give it unto him againſt whom he hath treſpaſſed;</hi> But if the man have no Kinſman to whom he ſhould reſtore the <hi>Dammage,</hi> or to be recompenced for the <hi>Treſpaſs,</hi> of Lying, and Detaining, and Concealing, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore related; Herein is uſed two ſeverall Tranſlations, for the plainer expreſſing of <hi>Treſpaſſes.</hi> Therefore <hi>John Burt,</hi> now that it will be proved againſt you, that you are guilty of conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Mr. <hi>Whetſtones</hi> Mortgage, and denying of it by Oath, and cancelling it, and altering it, as before related, you ought both to make Reſtitution to me, and to humble your ſelf alſo, which you will finde Chriſt taught to men when he was upon Earth, which ſtrengtheneth this Scripture, and maketh a threefold Teſtimony againſt you, or any obſtinate Lyer or Concealer, or falſe Swearer, and ſure you ought to obſerve it, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form thereunto, <hi>Matt.</hi> 5.24, 25. <hi>Therefore if thou bring thy Gift before the Aaltar, and there remembreſt that thy Brother hath ought againſt thee, leave there thy Gift before the Aaltar, And go thy way,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:118754:18"/> firſt be reconciled to thy Brother, and then come offer thy Gift.</hi> Jeſus ſpeaking to his Diſciples about offences, ſaid, <hi>Take heed to your ſelves,</hi> Luk. 17.1.3, 4. <hi>If thy Brother treſpaſſe against thee, rebuke him, and if he repent forgive him, And if he treſpaſſe againſt thee ſeven times in a day, and ſeven times in a day turn again to thee, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I repent, thou ſhalt forgive him;</hi> Thus you ſee by Scripture proved, That for <hi>falſe ſwearings</hi> about things loſt and conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or taken deceitfully, or violently, or wrongfully gotten, or if it were delivered one to keep, the principall ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to him to whom it appertaineth, with a <hi>Fift part</hi> more alſo, or the next Kinſman, and I am ſure you know not any ſo neer as my ſelf; nay you binde me in 500. l. and Articles to to you, I being the Eldeſt Son of our Father deceaſed, to ſue out <hi>Letters</hi> of <hi>Adminiſtration</hi> under the ſeale of the <hi>Prerogative Court,</hi> and therein to Diſcover the Eſtate, or any part or parcel thereof; Wherefore I by theſe Lines demand from you a true and reall Diſcovery, and ſatisfaction in ſome meaſure porpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable, that is <hi>Whetſtones</hi> Mortgage for 100. l. and the uſe thereof for three Years paſt at Chriſtmaſs laſt, reſtored me, and my Dividend of the Mortgage of St. <hi>Edmonds Burie,</hi> and the right and Intereſt of all Monies or Writings by you conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, that belongeth to our deceaſed Fathers Eſtate, or did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long thereunto, and I require, that you receive theſe Rebukes and Inſtructions in love, and ſet your ſelf to obſerve them, and ſhew it by your Anſwer hereunto, that I may receive you, and imbrace you, and forgive you: <hi>Jaacob,</hi> who in his youth, by his Mothers perſwaſions and ſubtilty, ſubplanted his Elder Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Eſau,</hi> and cauſed <hi>Iſaac</hi> thereat to tremble, and after was faine to fly, and leave both Father and Mother for fear of loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his Life by his provoked <hi>Elder Brother,</hi> as was told him by their Mother, yet many years after, he journeying neer <hi>Eſau</hi> his Elder Brother, at his return from <hi>Prdan Aram, Jaacob</hi> ſent Meſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ngers to call his Elder Brother <hi>Eſau</hi> Lord, and to deſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> he might finde g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ace in his ſight, and ſent him a great Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſent, to appeaſe his Elder Brother <hi>Eſau,</hi> that ſo he might be again accepted; and the Meſſengers were commanded to ſay, <hi>It is a
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:118754:19"/> Preſent, thy Servant</hi> Jaacob <hi>hath ſent unto my Lord</hi> Eſau; and when <hi>Eſau</hi> had accepted, and imbraced his Brother <hi>Jaacob,</hi> and reconciled himſelf to him; <hi>I have ſeen thy face</hi> (ſaith <hi>Jaacob) as if I had ſeen the face of God, in that thou wert pleaſed with me;</hi> therefore Experience as well as Scripture teacheth, <hi>How plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant a thing it is for Brethren to live together in amity, in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> and <hi>Prov.</hi> 18.19. you may read, <hi>A Brother offended is harder to be won then a ſtrong City, and their Contentions are like the Barrs of a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle;</hi> and though your abuſes to our Father deceaſed have been very great, and thoſe Abuſes and Provocations you have offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to me herein related, if you will ſay, <hi>it repenteth you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,</hi> and ſubmit your ſelf as <hi>Jaacob</hi> did, and receive theſe my M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ngers to you of Love, and Peace; for open rebuke is better then ſecret love, for the heart of a man diſpoſing, and the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer of the tongue, are both from the Lord, <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.1. Theſe Lines (my Meſſengers) penned by Gods Aſſiſtance, are to deſire you, You will not let Satan fill your heart with bitterneſſe, or harden it any longer, or to conſpire againſt me any more evil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; but receive the invitation of <hi>Reconciliation,</hi> that we may keep the Feaſte approaching, before the Lawyers Terme, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with the <hi>old Leaven,</hi> neither with the <hi>leaven of Malice and Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs,</hi> but with the <hi>unleavened bread of Sincerity and Truth,</hi> that God may receive Glory therein, our Fathers Name honored thereby, and our ſelves Eſtabliſhed, to our enemies aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that they may ſay, you have demeaned your ſelf as the Son of our deceaſed Father, not delighting in Fraudes or Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, to deſtroy your Fathers Elder Son, and the Eſtate alſo; which if you thus Declare your ſelf, I hope, I ſhall not onely receive you with the Spirit of meekneſs, but I ſhall receive you as a loving Chriſtian Brother, that might be ſaid to be faithful and deare unto me; and I ſhall labour alſo to reſtore you in all <hi>meekneſſe;</hi> All which will vex your Viperous brood, either <hi>Henry Wood,</hi> that mally part fellow, or any others, who expect to get by keeping you at Diſcord, and flatter you, That either <hi>Common Law</hi> or <hi>Equitie</hi> will bear you or them out in any frau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulent, or unjuſt Actions, for Truth is ſtrong, and will prevail
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:118754:19"/> above all the Enemies thereof; Thus beleeve: Captain <hi>Natha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nael Burt,</hi> the Eldeſt Son of his deceaſed Father, from whom he beleeveth oy you proceeded, and therefore truely deſireth your good in <hi>Christ Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my Houſe in</hi> Windmill Court, <date>
                     <hi>Aprill</hi> 6. 1655.</date> 
                  <hi>where I expect your Anſwer within</hi> 6 <hi>dayes, otherwiſe expect to have it Printed, that truth may appear, as it is plain truth, declared to publick view.</hi>
               </dateline>
               <signed>By N. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SEe and diſcern what great advantages, Practiſers have belonging to that is called Law, Juſtice and Right, or Equity to make themſelves rich by defending or plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for Concealers, Combinators, Defrauders, detainers of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens Profits and rights, who labour by Demurring, lying and falſe ſwearing to colour it, and not to be brought to light; for <hi>every one that doth evill, hateth the light, least his deeds ſhould be made manifeſt, or reproved;</hi> and theſe Practiſers do not only labour to extinguiſh Truth, but at length, many times themſelves poſſeſſe that Inheritance or Portion belongs to thoſe whom they have hightened by their Diſſentions; Let all Fathers be intreated, if they have any Eſtate to leave their Children, to diſpoſe of it by Will, to avoid diſcord, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcention among Brethren, and the eating up of their Eſtates by the Ravening Eſtate deſtroying Practiſers belonging moſt of them to that Hell fraught with Iniquitie, and Lyers called <hi>The High Court of Chancery;</hi> And obſerve alſo thus; by <hi>John Burts</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:118754:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> Combination, am I kept bare of Moneys, &amp; by the Charge and loſs I daily feel, am neceſſitated, &amp; was fain to render my body to Priſon to ſave my Bayl from the <hi>malice</hi> of <hi>Peter Tomſon,</hi> who red a Daughter of mine in ſtead of marrying of her, who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying alſo with <hi>John Burt,</hi> forced her to make an <hi>Affidavit</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me in <hi>Chancery,</hi> without any <hi>ſubpena</hi> thereto, to pleaſe him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd her Husband, would perſwade her alſo, if ſhe obeyed him not herein, how ſhould he live in Peace with her or could he love her, if ſhe would not be ruled by him, and doe what he would have her doe, though againſt her owne Father: Is not this unrighteous Brat, full of Malignity, malitiouſn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſe and Envy? and is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e not diſſobedient, that would combine to ſtop his Wives Father from receiving ſeverall Monies to diſſable him to pay him, and then to throw him into Priſon; Is not ſuch a one without Chriſtianity? though he <hi>breaketh bread</hi> with Mr. <hi>Nerton,</hi> and may he not be ſaid to be without <hi>naturall affection,</hi> without underſtanding, inplacable, unmercifull, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.28, 29, 30, 31, 32. and m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y it not be ſaid, that ſuch who Act thus, are <hi>delivered up,</hi> or <hi>given over to a Reprobate minde,</hi> which the Marginall Notes render thus, <hi>into a mad and froward minde,</hi> whereby it commeth to paſſe that the Conſcience be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing once put out, and having almoſt no more remorſe of ſinne, men run headlong into all kinde of miſchief; thus Diabolicall Practiſers of the Law will ſell the Right and Intereſt of the Righteous Perſon for a pair of ſhooes, or a piece of bread, thus are thy People eaten up all the day long by them as bread, but theſe Gormorants m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y in time be cauſed to Vomit up their morſells again, for as the Crown indureth not to every gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, ſo Riches are not for ever; for though the wayes of wicked men, and ſuch who are greedy of gaines, would take away the Life and Liberty of the owners thereof <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.19. <hi>Malice ſhall ſlay the wicked, and they that hate the Righteous ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, for though the troubles and afflictions of the Righteous are many, The Lord heareth, and delivereth them out of all their troubles,</hi> Pſal. 34.17.19, 21. But theſe Politick <hi>Foxes,</hi> and other ſubtill ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine fellows, who pretend they are Lawyers, but indeed
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:118754:20"/> they are Enemies to the Law both of God, and of <hi>England,</hi> and alſo the Peoples <hi>Priviledges</hi> and <hi>Liberties,</hi> and ſuch <hi>Countors</hi> or <hi>Pleaders,</hi> whether Sergeants, Councellors or Attorneys, Solici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors or other the Plaintiffs or Defendants Freind, either Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor or Proctors; For though Lawyers ſay, an <hi>Engliſhman</hi> is not to <hi>Pleade</hi> his own Caſe, yet that ancient Law-book called <hi>The Mirrour of Juſtices,</hi> will tell you, <hi>Though every one be not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to Pleade, ſome are admitted to pleade in all Actions without</hi> Tutors, <hi>and ſome but in fellonies;</hi> and where any Perſon is not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable, or in a Capacitie; therein <hi>Countors</hi> or <hi>Pleaders</hi> are allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to defend their <hi>Clyents Cauſes,</hi> according to the Rules of <hi>Law,</hi> and the Cuſtomes of the Realme, and every one that knoweth not how to defend their Cauſes in Judgement; and there are many that do, ſaith the Author. <hi>pag.</hi> 65. 128. And therefore <hi>Pleaders</hi> are neceſſary; ſo that, that which the <hi>Plaintiffe,</hi> or Act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors cannot, or know not how to do themſelves, they may do by their Sergeants, Attorneys or Freinds; Again ſaith he, <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors</hi> are <hi>Sergeants</hi> skilfull in the Lawes of the Realm; who ſerve the Common People to declare and defend Actions in Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; And every <hi>Countor</hi> is chargeable by Oath, <hi>That he ſhall do no wrong nor falſitie;</hi> and alſo that he put no falſe <hi>Dilatories</hi> into Court, nor move or offer any falſe Corruptions, Deceits, Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings or falſe Lyes, nor conſents to any ſuch, nor falſe Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; and I ſay of the Law of <hi>England,</hi> next unto Gods Sacred Law, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 18. <hi>Which is good, if it be uſed lawfully,</hi> which is made for lawleſſe and diſſobedient Perſons, &amp;c. And for Lyars and Perjured Perſons, and one that Writt concerning Courts in King <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Eights</hi> time, ſaith, Note that an Oath ought to have three Companions, <hi>Truth, Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Judgement;</hi> And if that be wanting, it is no Oath but Perjurie; and St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>That the Law is made for offenders, for Lyers and perjured Perſons; Perjury</hi> is called a <hi>great offence,</hi> whether in a procured Witneſs, or acted by one Perſonally in his own Caſe, when it ſhall be diſcovered and proved to be his owne Act, that by his own conſent and agreement, he ſhall wilfully a d corru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ly in any Court of <hi>Chancery,</hi> or Court of <hi>Probates,</hi> &amp;c. formerly called
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:118754:21"/> the <hi>Prerogative Court,</hi> or <hi>Spirituall Court,</hi> or in any of the other Courts formerly belonging to the Kings or Queens of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> All the Judges of <hi>England,</hi> 9. <hi>Ed.</hi> 4.53. did manifeſtly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, That the <hi>Chancery, Kings Bench, Common Pleas,</hi> and <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer</hi> be all the Kings Courts, and have been time out of minde, and ſo that no man knoweth which of them is moſt auncient, uſed 19. <hi>Ed.</hi> 4.4. and <hi>Cookes</hi> Preface to the Eighth <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port,</hi> practiſe of the High Court of <hi>Chancery, pag.</hi> 56. and <hi>choice Caſes</hi> of <hi>Chancery. pag.</hi> 141. A <hi>Subpoena</hi> was awarded out of this <hi>Court,</hi> to Anſwer a <hi>Bill</hi> of <hi>Perjury,</hi> committed by the Defendant <hi>Goze,</hi> in ſwearing for the impotencie of the other Defendant, whereas he was not above 50 years old, and not able to travell, <hi>Griffeth</hi> plaintiff, <hi>ap Jenkin</hi> and <hi>Goze</hi> Defendants, <hi>Anno</hi> 21, 22. <hi>El<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>z.</hi> and are not the <hi>Courts</hi> now called His <hi>Highneſs Courts,</hi> the Lord <hi>Protect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r;</hi> The <hi>Chancery</hi> had a Soveraigne Power above <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll other <hi>Courts</hi> of <hi>Equitie,</hi> it being a <hi>Court</hi> of the diſtribution of the Kings own <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and Bills are Exhibitted here in the vacancie of the Lord <hi>Keeper,</hi> or <hi>Chancellor</hi> to his own Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Perſon, <hi>viz.</hi> To the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſtie, in His High <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Chancery, Practice</hi> of <hi>Chancery unfoulded,</hi> pag. 35. and will you not ſuffer the diſtribution of His <hi>Highneſs Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> viz. <hi>OLIVER</hi> Lord <hi>Protector,</hi> the preſent Governour, whoſe Name you know all men are now to obey, to be diſtributed in His Highneſs High <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Chancery, Perjury</hi> was fined, exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined and punniſhed, Tranſaactions of the the High Court of <hi>Chancery, pag.</hi> 156. 157. <hi>Perjury</hi> to be examined here, <hi>Halſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Browne,</hi> notwithſtanding the cauſe, was diſmiſſed. 16. <hi>Eliz. fol.</hi> 401. Free-born <hi>contra leaſure</hi> in <hi>Trin.</hi> 20. <hi>Jac. li.</hi> B. <hi>Mound. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Culme,</hi> 40. pounds coſt given for <hi>Perjury</hi> in <hi>Mich.</hi> 14. <hi>Car.</hi> in the j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dgement <hi>Roll,</hi> the 37. <hi>H,</hi> 8 between <hi>Baskervile</hi> and <hi>Guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ams,</hi> ſet on the Pillory for procuring <hi>Perjury</hi> in the Spirituall Court; with divers others, not herein named, who were puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by <hi>Chancery</hi> Power; And I hope, ſince we have ſuch Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, when His Highneſs <hi>Conſcience</hi> ſhall be diſtributed in His <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Chancery,</hi> as it hath been in other Kings time, or Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments, The Juſtices of other Courts of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> have
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:118754:21"/> their Authority by <hi>Writt</hi> or <hi>Patient</hi> under the <hi>Great Seal</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> being the Seal of <hi>Chancery,</hi> which is Committed to the Lord <hi>Chancellour,</hi> or <hi>Keeper</hi> by the King, together with the diſtribution of his own <hi>Conſcience;</hi> Thus have Kings promiſed to Govern <hi>Gods People,</hi> to maintain &amp; defend their Perſons, and their Goods, in Peace, by Rules of Law; and this hath His High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe the Lord <hi>Protector</hi> ſworne to Govern by the Lawes, Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes and <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> of this Nation; ſeeking the Nations Peace, and cauſing Juſtice and Law to be equally Adminiſtred. This He ſigned <hi>December</hi> 16, 1653.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>O. CROMVVELL.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>ANd this ought the peaceable People of the Three <hi>Nations</hi> to clayme and expect from His <hi>Highneſs,</hi> and to endeavor peaceably to obtain, and under this <hi>Protection</hi> of His <hi>Highneſs O. CROMWELL,</hi> declared <hi>Lord Protector,</hi> as aboveſaid, I Claim and require the defence of my Perſon from violence, and inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and the Right, Title, Property, and Intereſt in my owne Goods and Eſtate, in Peace according to Gods <hi>Law,</hi> and the Rules of the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> which comes neereſt to Gods <hi>Law,</hi> from fraudulent concealment, and from falſe Judgement, for it is Written. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.150.165. <hi>Great peace have they which love thy Law, and nothing ſhall offend them; but they that f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>llow after miſchief, are farr from thy Law.</hi> I read in a Book, called, <hi>For the ſacred Law of the Land, Cap.</hi> 1. The Precepts of <hi>Law</hi> are (as <hi>Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cton, De. Nat. Deo.</hi> 1. To live honeſtly, wrong no man, give eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man his own; Our Saviour comprehends the ſame in one Rule alſo; <hi>Do as you would be done to,</hi> and this is called the <hi>Law</hi> and the <hi>Prophets, Matth.</hi> 7.12. Preſidents have only ſo much of <hi>Law,</hi> as they have of Juſtice; <hi>Ch. Juſt.</hi> Hub. 270. Thoſe and <hi>Lawes</hi> are built upon <hi>Reaſon</hi> &amp; <hi>Juſtice, Law</hi> and <hi>Justice</hi> are inſeparable. We read in our Old <hi>Lawes,</hi> 1. <hi>Bract. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 4. In the time of the <hi>Daniſh Kings,</hi> right was buried in the Realme, the <hi>Lawes</hi> and <hi>Customes</hi> ſlept together in their time, ſaith <hi>Fleta,</hi> Judgement and Peace goe together, 1. <hi>c.</hi> 29. and it is a good <hi>Conſequence</hi>) that
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:118754:22"/> 
                  <hi>ſo common Justice and Right may be done to every Man; Britton</hi> u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites <hi>Peace</hi> &amp; <hi>Law</hi> (in another place) as fully; <hi>Peace,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>cannot well be without Law. fol.</hi> 1. the Arbitrary will of man can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be <hi>Law, Lawes cannot be juſt, without they be certaine.</hi> It is the beſt <hi>Law</hi> ſayes the Illuſtrious Viſcount St. <hi>Albon. Aphoriſm</hi> 8. which leaves leaſt to the Arbitrarineſs of the Judge, ſaith <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis</hi> White the Authour thereof in his <hi>Preface,</hi> pag. 18. No man is aſſured, He ſhall either keep his Eſtate, or tranſmit it to Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, but by the <hi>Lawes,</hi> let the Inherritance be what it can be, there is more taken from the Lawes, which direct and fix the Diſcent, and <hi>wall it in,</hi> then from our <hi>Parents;</hi> The pooreſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitated man, amidſt the calamityes of this preſent life, who li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth under Oppreſſion and miſery, even cruſh'd almoſt to pieces, which might make him loath his <hi>Condition,</hi> he would yet be more unhappy, were not the Law his Sanctuary; and here now being come to the juſt &amp; wholſom <hi>Sanction</hi> of the <hi>Lawes,</hi> when they are obeyed and Reverenced, I ſhall herein reſt, and make it my <hi>Sanctuary,</hi> as of old it hath been to our Anceſtors, committing my ſelf in ſpirit to <hi>Jeovah</hi> the Great <hi>Law-giver, who is King</hi> of <hi>Kings, and Lord of Lords the Mighty GOD,</hi> and my <hi>Perſon</hi> and Eſtate, and <hi>Franchiſe,</hi> and <hi>Right,</hi> unto the <hi>Protector Ordained</hi> and ſet up by God, as <hi>Ruler</hi> and <hi>Governour</hi> of the <hi>Three Nations,</hi> and ought to be God's <hi>Miniſter</hi> for our good, <hi>for Rulers are not a terrour for good Works, but for evill.</hi> Rom. 13.1, 2, 3, 4. and to His Highneſs <hi>Conſcience distributed,</hi> in His <hi>Highneſs Courts;</hi> and in time, I hope to ſee <hi>Englands Lawes, Statutes</hi> and <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> maintained, and <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Law</hi> equally adminiſtred, and all <hi>falſe Judgements</hi> rectified, and Judges puniſhed, and the abuſive Practiſe in His <hi>Highneſs Courts</hi> reformed, for the <hi>Peoples</hi> tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity and <hi>Peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>And ſo prayeth the Pen-man hereof,</hi> N. B.</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>
                        <hi>Aprill.</hi> 9. 1655.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:118754:22"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Philoſtratus Philodemius,</head>
            <p>WHo tendered the Conſideration of <hi>Seaſonable Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> to His <hi>Highneſs</hi> the Lord Protector and His Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, relating to the <hi>High Court</hi> of <hi>Chancery,</hi> and the <hi>Fees</hi> and <hi>Proceedings</hi> thereof, and in the 56, 57, 58, 59, 60, 61, <hi>pages</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, in the Table, where he ſets down the then <hi>standing Fees</hi> were taken, what will content the Labourer, and what will be ſaved to the <hi>Common Wealth;</hi> The <hi>Six Clerks</hi> demanded, ſaith he, by vertue of a Pattent from the late King a gaine for Inrollment, the <hi>ſix Clerks,</hi> and the <hi>Three Masters</hi> of the <hi>Petty Bagge;</hi> they alſo demanded great <hi>Fees</hi> by colour of a <hi>Pattent</hi> or <hi>Charter</hi> from the late King, and the <hi>Examiners Office,</hi> demanded alſo by colour of a <hi>Pattent</hi> from the late King; ſaith the ſaid Authour, the <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poena Office is</hi> a <hi>Monopoly;</hi> Reader, I pray obſerve, at the <hi>Subpoena Office,</hi> they have ſubmitted to the Regulation of the <hi>Ordinance</hi> made by the Lord <hi>Protector</hi> and his Council. I pray why ſhall not the reſt of the <hi>Pattentees</hi> ſubmit to this <hi>Ordinance,</hi> as well as the <hi>Subpoena</hi> Monopoly Office? alſo might not the <hi>Pattent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees</hi> and <hi>Monopolizers,</hi> which were under the late King, deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders by colour of <hi>Pattents</hi> from the King, extort monies from the People as theſe now doe, although they are commanded o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, which for their Information is Exemplified in the Table of <hi>Fees</hi> belonging to the ſaid <hi>Ordinance,</hi> in the 66 Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of the ſaid <hi>Ordinance</hi> you may read thus, That if any Regiſter, chief Clerke, Examiner, Attorney of the ſaid Court, or Officer for making <hi>Subpoenas,</hi> ſhall either directly, or indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly, demand take or receive any other <hi>Fees,</hi> or ſum of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, then what is contained in the Table annexed, &amp;c. And every ſuch Offence ſhalbe, and is hereby Ordained, adjudged and declared, and ſhall be reputed and taken to be <hi>Extortion,</hi> and ſhall be puniſhed as <hi>Extortion,</hi> and that every <hi>Perſon</hi> or <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> ſo offending, and thereof convicted, ſhall be, and are here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:118754:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> diſſabled to beare any Office of Truſt or P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>fit in the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Wealth;</hi> you may herein ſee that the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>poe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Officers have ſubmitted to the ſaid Ordinance, and the table <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f <hi>Fees</hi> thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to annexed, leaſt they ſhould looſe their ſeverall and reſpective Places, and be diſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bled for nonconformance thereunto, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo ordained by the Authority aforeſaid. The other Officers of <hi>Chancery</hi> that are greater in Place, can read better then I, though they will not obey thereunto, <hi>Diſtinction</hi> the 65. <hi>It is Ordained, That the Maſter of the</hi> Rolls, <hi>and Maſters of the</hi> Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery <hi>reſpectively ſhall not demand, take or receive any other</hi> Fees <hi>then what are contained in the Table annexed, and that every offence in that behalf ſhall be, and is hereby adjudged and declared to be Extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and ſhall be puniſhed as Extortion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Reader, This Ordinance muſt be obeyed, as all the reſt this preſent <hi>Power</hi> hath made and Ordained, maugre all choſe that call themſelves Lawyers, or their dependants, ſee and obſerve the <hi>Subpoena</hi> Officers belonging to the Lord <hi>Protectors</hi> Highneſs Court of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> the <hi>Chancery,</hi> in which I pray you all to help me in your <hi>Prayers,</hi> that God will Enable <hi>O. CROMWELL</hi> who was ſworn Lord <hi>Protector</hi> the Sixteenth of <hi>December,</hi> 1653. by the Lords <hi>Commiſſioners,</hi> they Adminiſtring the ſaid Oath to him, that he may diſtribute a good <hi>Conſcience</hi> to the <hi>Peoples</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief in Equitie and Juſtice, that his face may appear as an Angel of God;</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>So prayes Captain,</hi> N. B</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
